it's on me there we go
all right we're live we're live holy cow
hello YouTube we are live in Phoenix we
are at Comerica theater I've got this
Jordan Peterson guy
I'm Simon I'm somehow hosting on his
channel but that doesn't seem right
we're about to do what are maybe 13 14
15 they're all starting to blend yeah
good wardrobe department I feel a very
sharp this theater in Phoenix is one of
the most interesting ones yet it's it's
very big yeah
stories high inside yeah so about about
4,000 people waiting in there it's about
105 in Phoenix today yeah they were
actually only here to purchase the
orchid very much I literally went to the
gym twice today to sweat indoors because
it was so hot outdoors but we've been
bouncing around we just did three stops
in tenses and what I say to you every
night I say it before we started then at
the end it's like man everything that
they say about this man about this tour
about everything going on here it's
completely the reverse yeah yeah
interesting yeah well I spend lectures
talking to people it's usually about a
hundred and fifty people that I get to
say hello to yeah and everybody has 15
seconds or so to tell me a story but
they don't they're saying audio is
really low audio is low all right we're
gonna talk louder okay all right we're
gonna talk louder how's that let's see
if we can pick it up yeah so yeah Oh a
letter G Peter come on man so I talked
to about 150 people afterwards and they
they all have a story to tell me but
most of the stories are variants on a
theme which is that they're happy to
listen to the lectures because it's
helping them clarify their thinking or
providing them with words that they
haven't had before yeah describe things
they know that be true or they tell me
that they're doing there's a couple or
that there's father and son there or
father of the daughter or mother and the
daughter and they're getting along
better or it's a couple that's just
decided to get engaged and their
relationship is better or a father who's
he was doing better with his kids none
of its political very little of its
political
yeah it's maybe it's maybe 10% political
and I'll talk to the camera for a second
for this because every day when they
tell you that Jordans you know it's
angry white men right that's it okay
first off he's I would guess it's about
6040 usually male to female there are
gay people there are black people white
people Asian people there were Muslims
last night and Jews I mean the whole
thing all of that diversity that
actually doesn't matter it's all there
and they just they just consistently lie
about it
well I think that it seems to me that
the let's say the mainstream media types
that have been peering me in various
ways don't have a lexicon for dealing
with a phenomena that's primarily
psychological they have to make this
fundamentally political yeah the
political aspects of it you know insofar
as I'm not the family leftist for
example and but by the way you've been
slamming the the radical right to I mean
your whole thing I mean this is the the
irony of the situation is you talk about
the identity politics to the right and
the danger of that as much almost on
stage I don't like collectivists yeah I
think it's a bad route and I think it
takes us down the tribal path and I
think that the end destiny of a tribal
path is bloodshed and I don't care
whether it's the left or the right I'm
more perturbed about the left wing
because of their dominance in the
universities in particular and that's
what you know that's where Laura this
came from but it it's the collectivist
issue that's the that's at hand
and almost everything that we've been
talking about what I'm talking about
with the audience's about the Western
tradition of individual responsibility
essentially also not individual rights
although
they're part of the discussion yeah
that's funny to be but I would also say
been in the collectivist lexical and
there's no such thing as free speech and
there's really no such thing as
individual responsibility and so insofar
as I'm able to make a case for that that
makes me an enemy but even more
importantly it takes the dialogue
outside of their the way they frame the
world they don't know what to do about
it yeah I don't know how to handle it so
they invent an enemy essentially right
they don't really do the work
intellectually to counter the arguments
so they just do the same old thing we
were saying right before we started how
I didn't year and a half ago we didn't
even know each other no the first time
we ever did anything together was I
think it was November 2nd of 2016 which
was a day or two before the American
election it feels like a lifetime again
we did I just moved into my house I
didn't have my studio yet and we did a
little Google hangout thing and the
audio was terrible the video is bad and
you were telling me that the Pinocchio's
memory which now most dear audience
knows about and you were getting teary
eyed on it and it ended and I thought
and truly I've been excited to you I was
like I don't know exactly what to make
of this guy and then subsequently you
came on my show many times and we've
done a couple hours together and we did
sit down you Shapiro and it's like a
three month or two months this thing
just levels up levels up and it feels
more real it feels more concrete and and
we're all kind of growing together yeah
but I got to tell you man we crossed six
hundred thousand YouTube subscribers I
think on the same day
you got like 1.2 right now I'm almost at
800 I'm starting I like competition I do
like competition we do like that yeah
but it's just so cool watching this
whole thing grow well luckily as as
hundreds of millions of people come
online
gonna run out of audience yeah because
there's another two billion people to
join what to join the electronic web
with enough bandwidth to start streaming
videos so goes to me like this will
online video and audio and podcasts
world is just getting us legs underneath
it yeah god knows where it's gonna go
alright well since we're behind the
scenes in the green room let's just do a
couple behind-the-scenes things right
here first off just how you feelin while
doing this whole thing I'm my health is
improving very much yeah so yeah so
that's really that's really working out
well yeah I'm having a very nice time
with the audiences they're unbelievably
isn't it incredible I mean meeting these
people like just and literally
everything we haven't had one protester
no just everybody yes they're planning
something in Portland yeah well we'll
see about port really you know every
night after the show you meet a certain
amount of people afterwards and I
usually go out into the crowd
yeah there's hundreds sometimes
thousands of people wait it's like yeah
yeah good thing you're not a germaphobe
yeah yeah well the other thing too is if
if I protested in Richmond or or
Portland to any degree I'm gonna
videotape the lecture elite and put it
put it online and then people can see
what's being protested yeah I think so I
think that's the plan when we do these
they've pretty much been different every
single night I mean we've done about 15
shows and I I mix it up a little bit
every night you know there's a couple
jokes in there that are the mainstays
some lobster stuff and the rest but yeah
well you can't dispatch the lobsters
have to be in there but but you pretty
much have an hour and a half that you do
and then especially when we do the Q&A
after which is totally off-the-cuff
you're kind of just going in and out and
and sometimes you do three rules
sometimes you do a rule sometimes you
know rules and yeah it's kind of amazing
yeah well I'm trying to develop a very
large corpus of stories around each of
the chapters and then I can mix and
match them and I'm also trying to push
the ideas that I've been developing in
the book farther ahead with each talk
yeah and so I spent a lot of time
talking about the relationship between
hierarchies and
goals and and and difference in status
that's been a that's been a main theme
and the relationship between truth and
quality of existence that's another one
that there's a very powerful positive
relationship there necessary and so in
all of those themes you know there's no
end to the amount you can develop them
and each venue gives me an opportunity
to push it a little bit farther and
clarify what I'm thinking and get the
story a little bit tighter and see how B
or D and see how the individuals in the
audience are reacting yeah and so I like
the fact that you open with some
humorous intro and that the QA has a an
element of lightness and comedy in it
because one of the things I learned a
long time ago was that even if you're
dealing with something that's extremely
serious if you can't do it with the
comedic touch then you haven't got the
balance right even if it's deadly
serious stuff yeah and they look they
love it when when you make them laugh
sometimes accidentally even like they're
like they love that they really love
seeing that other's idea yeah that's
pretty cool yeah all right well you got
a show to get I do I guess I got a show
to do you but but you really got a show
you all right guys that's Jordan
Peterson I'm Dave Berman would you tell
these good people to subscribe to my
channel subscribe to Dave's damn channel
the subscribers far behind
[Laughter]
don't make me the bottom lobster guys I
get it he's the top lobster but can we
do it a second grab a lobster or
something all right all right it's gonna
be fun tonight and we look forward to
seeing you guys we're doing this through
through July and then you're continuing
into August yeah maybe September - yeah
you're gonna jump back in in September
all right awesome yeah great you know
thanks Johnny